Guide to the International Monitor Institute. Burma Videotapes, circa 1990-2002 RL.00605
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Burma Videotapes, circa 1990-2002, 287 videocassettes
  - Bared Face Production: Life on the Line, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:39:00] (Box 306, Video-cassette BU071)
    An investigation on human rights abuses based on the construction story of Yadana Pipeline in Burma across the Karen dominated area, by Karen Human Rights Commission, and Htoo La.
    The Pipeline built by Total and Unocal companies to deliver gas from Adaman sea to Thailand, providing much needed cash for State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC). SLORC made the area into a no man's land. They rounded up villages and drove the residents away to labor camps. SLORC relocated villages and fenced the area like a concentration camp. They forced people to work for the construction.
    The refugees said: "We have to work with bare hands and no tools. "People's movements were restricted like in the prison camps.
    Lun Davies, the Oil Concession Manager, took advantage of harsh labor.
    Simon Bilennes, Ethical Investment Analyst, said that refugees told a consistent story: SLORC mistreated people and used forced labor.
    Taking a journey across the Burmese jungle with Karen National Union (KNU) to fire free zone. It was Christmas Eve in a Burmese jungle and the Andamen Sea, Ma Thidainterviewed Bill Richardson. "Burma needs much more responsible investment."
    There were protests against Unocal across the United States.
    SLORC attacked some villages and the KNU defended them. People hid in pits.
    Scenes include deserted villages and bloodstained floors. According to video, SLORC broke into homes shot people, carried away belongings, destroyed property and left.
    Senator Byron Rushing said: "The Clinton Administration should condemn Burma by taking some decisive measures."
    Thida interviewed some Unocal officials. The official denied accusations: "You are trying to make us look bad."
    On the actual work site, soldiers went to the villages to steal, loot and kill people. A girl's mother was shot while hugging her.
    International pressures like those applied to South Africa would cripple the SLORC investors. Senator Rushing said it was not easy because people had to work hard to get the White house to act on the issue. The British parliament member said: "The sanction must be extended."
    People believe that sanction is ultimate act.
  - Images Asia: Right in the Cross Fire, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:18:00] (Box 305, Video-cassette BU073)
    Edited report by Jude Smith, the European Human Rights Foundation, in 1995 (English).
    Karen refugees: Women were forcibly taken away by soldiers. We have never seen them again. State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC) terrorizes the ethnic minorities. Women and children were brutalized, a soldier confirmed. There were unbelievable abuses. Some known abuses were conducted by Sgt. Ba Gyi. A girl was picking vegetables but Ba Gyi took her and raped her. She lay unconscious next to the road. She was later sent to a hospital, but she died.
    In the Tachileik town, 1995, soldiers exposed themselves in front of the girls. Some pointed guns at women, looted jewelry and raped them. "We took everything from every village we went across. If one could not pay he had to work. We have been on the move since 1995. We left whenever we heard gun shots. Family structure was destroyed. I have no parents and I don't know where they are."
    Malaria and anemia are common. Children suffer from bad health and poverty and receive little education. They shifted schools into work skill training camps. They transported women to Thailand to meet the Thai demand for its sex market and for cheap labor. Ranong, a Burmese, found this a disappointment. "Many Burmese are exploited. Many have been sold. If dictatorship stays in power for long we are in trouble."
  - Amateur Footage: Los Angeles Residents Meet Myanmar Ambassador U Win Tin, NTSC VHS [TRT 10:20:00] (2 copies) (Box 305, Video-cassette BU074)
    Produced by: Personal Footage
    A meeting between State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC) Ambassador to the United States and Los Angeles residents in La Puente, in a Buddhist temple in Los Angeles, March 16, 1997(in Burmese).
    The visiting Ambassador Tin Win met Burmese exiled community in Los Angeles, entertained questions of the SLORC position. He denied the 1988 massacre and took a solid stand that SLORC was doing the best for the country. Dr Aung Khin: "We will win. "The ambassador was accompanied by U Sein Tun andDaw Khin Win May.
    Tin Win: "I'll tell you know the truth about Myanmar."
    On the cease fire situation: "There will be trust after cease fire."
    On the failed negotiation with Karen National Union (KNU): "We have discussed with the NLD but they withdrew." He blamed previous government.
    U Nyunt Maung told Tin Win that soldiers robbed the people. Boys were forcibly taken away by SLORC. Tin Win: "I will investigate and respond."
    Insufficient investment is common among the newly opened-up countries. Internal economy has significantly improved.
    He defended SLORC's stand on the refusal to hand over power for economic advance.
    There was a tough argument as to what market economy should be. What is market economy according to SLORC? Rice export and local distribution procedure.
    They also talked about special colleges for military services, the sagaing massacre and SLORC inaction.
  - KCAL9: The Burma Forum L.A. Protesting Union Oil Company of California (Unocal), NTSC VHS [TRT 00:04:00] (2 copies) (Box 305, Video-cassette BU075)
    Produced by: KCAL Channel 9
    Network: burma forum
    News Clips from KCAL Channel 9 on December 12 1996, called "Protest Against Unocal" by the Burma Forum Los Angeles.(in English)
    Activists tied themselves to the Unocal truck. Thirteen were arrested.
    Indy Tiny was charged with trespassing. Also arrestedwere Khin Maung Shwe, Taw Myo Shwe and Ko Latt.
  - Aung San Suu Kyi acceptance of Nobel Prize, 1991, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:60:00] (Box 305, Video-cassette BU076)
  - Earth Right Int'l: L.A. protest against State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC), NTSC VHS [TRT 00:45:00] (Box 306, Video-cassette BU077)
    Produced by: Earth Right Int'l
    Action against Unocal in Burma, in December 1996.
  - Independent Production: To Ease the Pain in Gangaw Wood, NTSC VHS [TRT 01:34:00] (Box 306, Video-cassette BU078)
    Produced by: Myanmar Local Production
    "To Ease the Pain in the Gangaw Wood," by Zagana.
    Episodes of humor were directed against the Burmese regime, in 1994 (in Burmese).
    Dat Si, disappointed over the present situation in Burma, drank petrol to kill himself. The petrol was fake.
    There were jokes about local transportation, local customs of courtship, economic hardship and scarcity. There were also jokes about the justice system, death and the loss of rights.
    The "Gangaw Myaing Anyaint" was to honor the Diamond Jubilee of Rangoon University - six politically motivated comedians performed along with a famous dancer, May Than Nu.
    Zagana, Kingkong. Ngapyawgyaw, Mitta, Ayaing, Godzilla appeared and criticized the social and political weakness of State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC).
  - PBS: The OpiumKings, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:40:00] (Box 306, Video-cassette BU079)
    Produced by: Front Line USA
    Edited report on Front Line, May 20, 1997, by Adrian Cowell (in English), funded by PBS.
    Shan in Burma was founded in 1962 to topple Burmese strong man Ne Win, took arms and began guerrilla warfare. Adrian Cowell traveled to opium area in Burma in 1964. Chris Monges never returned.
    There was an ineffective offensive and lack of funding of the Shan State Army (SSA) taxed opium trade.
    Opium consumed away the political aims.Sao Boon Tai: "We will dominate opium trade to finance our army."
    In 1972, some switched sides and worked with Burmese government.
    Law Sit Han, one of the kings, said that the KoKand Army transported 700 mules of opium to Thailand and brought consumer goods to Burma. Across the valley they clashed with another revolutionary group.
    Losithan was forced to disband his army by Newin and came to Rangoon to live a new life. Lawsithan shook hands with the SSA people. He called US to buy off opium and burned them or people would continue the trade. Burma produced 180 tons a year and traded them. "We don't know how to manufacture heroin. We have to ask traders from Tacheleik. We knew how to make morphine."
    Locithan was arrested in Thailand and extradited to Burma.
    There was power vacuum in opium trade. Khunsa was the second king of opium. Joe Nalas, Congressman in Khun Sa's headquarters, suggested a Drug Committee in White House. Peter Borne opposed. He rejected Khunsa and helped Burma, giving them helicopters and airplanes. That did not yield good results. 80 million dollars of aid was given to Burma, but it was stopped in 1988.
    In 1992, Cowell returned. There were many more SSA soldiers. Opium production had grown.
    SSA and Burmese army were in conflict in Maung Chuat valley. Khin Myunt in Rangoon Lawsithan negotiated opium.
    Khunsa attempted to have ceasefire with army. US condemned the act.
  - TV Myanmar: SPDC Sponsored New Umbrella Installation Ceremony of Great Shwedagon Pagoda, April 1999, NTSC VHS [TRT 02:00:00] (Box 305, Video-cassette BU080)
    Edited report by TV Myanmar - the New Umbrella Installation Ceremony of Shwe Da Gon in Rangoon
    State Peace and Development Council (SPDC) attempted to stay in power. He followed the instruction of fortune tellers and palm readers.
    The SPDC claimed victory over the enemies.
    The top brass of SPDC attended the ceremony.
    Top SPCD sponsored monks and tens of thousands of devotees were also presented.
  - NHK (Japanese TV): Interview with Aung San Suu Kyi, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:30:00] (Box 305, Video-cassette BU081)
    Produced by: NHK Japan
    Aung San Suu Kyi on Japanese TV (NHK).
  - Amateur Footage: Jokes of Zagana, NTSC VHS [TRT 01:00:00] (Box 305, Video-cassette BU082)
    Produced by: Personal footage
    It included the best jokes about the State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC) by the comedian Zagana.
  - National League for Democracy (NLD): Free Burma Movement in USA, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:15:00] (Box 305, Video-cassette BU083)
    The edited footage of "Free Burma Movement in USA," by Free Burma Coalition (in Burma).
    There was a demonstration against Pepsi Co. Pepsi withdrew Burma Campaign.
    All levels of society of over 20 countries were enthusiastically involved in condemning the State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC).
    The company Texaco and some universities took part in the consumer boycott. They held portraits of Aung San Suu Kyi.
    "Economic boycott is a successful tool. SLORC is selling out the country, to expand the army to threaten the security of the people," said Suu Kyi.
    Cities in the United States are starting to introduce the selective purchasing ordinance to punish companies who do business with Burma.
    Under the leadership of Aung San Suu Kyi, the Burmese people took part in her struggle for democracy.
  - Free Burma Coalition: Pepsi's Burma Campaign, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:15:00] (Box 305, Video-cassette BU084)
    Produced by: Free Burma CoalitionZanni
    Pepsi Withdraws Campaign.
  - National League for Democracy (NLD): Anniversary of the Myannegone Massacre, June 21, 1989, NTSC VHS [TRT 02:00:00] (Box 305, Video-cassette BU085)
    U Tin OO and Daw Aung San Suu Kyi attend. They comment that one year ago today, the worst massacre happened. We gained a limited victory. U Tin Oo speaks extensively. A student representative speaks. Aung San Suu Kyi speaks.She says that the Burmese will never allow such leaders to rule again. "Struggle with us," she pleaded.
    At the Sagaing Office the army has blocked the area. Army trucks interrupt the program with loud speakers. People listen as U Tin Oo speaks at gun point.
    Aung San Suu Kyi says, "I speak to the army, too." Her attacks are directed at Ne Win and the army. She says that soldiers are not aliens from other planets, they are Burmese. She invites listeners to oppose the laws that were designed to oppress the Burmese.
    Army guards start to shoot toward the people. Some people are arrested. In the park, Aung San Suu Kyi approaches and lays flowers for the dead. She is arrested.Another participant is arrested, one is killed and one wounded by bullets.
    At Headquarters: U Tin Oo and Aung San Suu Kyi speak.
  - State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC) Production: Miss Puppy, NTSC VHS [TRT 2:14:00] (2 copies) (Box 295, Video-cassette BU086)
    Produced by: Myanmar Military and Psychological Warfare Department
    Fictional story.
    A group of young people flee Burma to fight for democracy. They are demoralized and worn out. Opportunists enter the scene, at the Thibawbo and Minthamee Karen National Union (KNU) Camp. A tragic ending follows for those who fled Burma.Attacks followed on democracy and student leaders such as Dr. Aung Khin and Saw Bo Mya. KNU abandons them in the cross fire. Dr. Aung Khin is seen in the KNU camp. Sexual and physical abuse of the KNU are described as well as presentations of landmine victims.
    Dramatized re-enactments of the revolution are shown as well as some factual misinformation about the armed democracy struggle and the Karen National Union.
  - Images Asia: Toward Freedom, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:30:00] (2 copies) (Box 295, Video-cassette BU087)
    Produced by: All Burma Student Democratic Front/Images Asia
    Brief scene of the 1988 massacre. Ne Win gave his threat.
    Armed students were along the River Moi (Thaung Yin Myit).
    In the All Burma Students' Democratic Front (ABSDF) camps, medical workers were providing service to refugees.
  - NHK (Japanese TV): Democracy Struggle and Bloody Crackdown in 1988, NTSC VHS [TRT 01:09:00] (Box 295, Video-cassette BU088)
    Produced by: NHKJapan
    People are marching peacefully, chanting. Gunfire is heard across the field. People fall. Many take cover in the trees.One receives a direct hit, others are hit several times. One falls. Someone cries, "We have no arms!" They cry out but the soldiers keep shooting. Some people are seen being comforted, the wounded are carried away. Soldiers are well-positioned and aiming at people. A policeman yells, "Keep shooting until they shoot us."
    A brief news clip from TV Burma: "The Abolished Socialist Program Party."
    In Shwedagon, Ne Win is with some diplomats. Sein Lwin takes over. On people's uprising, Aung San Suu Kyi and U Aung Gyi speak out. Aung Gyi expresses the general deterioration of the Burmese situation. U Tin Oo: "Victory is at hand." One Democracy activist came from Japan. A protest rally in front of the Burmese Embassy. Aung Gyi leads the demonstration. Police and army officers are interviewed. U Nu explains the suffering of the people. There are clashes and battles. Bodies are in the rivers. Piles of bodies are seen after the coup. General hospital scenes are shown.
    Scenes of the Rangoon river bank: soldiers stand guard everywhere. Smoke rises from the crematorium.
    U Ne Win threatens: "The army will shoot straight, not into the air. Anyone who opposes the government will pay the price of death."
    The movement of the people continues in spite of the threat. Upside-down flags are waved. Aung Gyi leads an uprising.
    Daw Aung San Suu Kyi arrives on the scene. Barricades and check points are everywhere around town. Teashop discussions take place. Some spies are accused of penetrating the crowds. MI agents interrogate citizens. Soldiers join the people.
    Saw Maung leads State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC) and takes power on Sept 17, 1988.
    Aung San Suu Kyi: "Our people have shown solid discipline."
    The Army opens fire again on Sept 18, killing thousands more, and takes firm power. SLORC claims insurgents cause damage and only the army can take care of the people.
  - Amateur Footage: Refugees in Thailand, NTSC VHS [TRT 01:00:30] (Box 295, Video-cassette BU089)
    Produced by: IRC Women's Commsion
    The tape shows victims of the civil war and the hopelessness of women and children.
  - Images Asia: Message to UN Commission on Human Rights from Aung San Suu Kyi, March 1988, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:18:00] (Box 295, Video-cassette BU090)
    Produced by: Altsean and Images Asia
    Human rights pertain to all human beings. Those who are repressed are not the same as those who are free. The case of Burma is not only concerned with Burma but is representative of the suffering of people around the world.UN resolutions on Burma, in place since 1989, have never been implemented. The resolution must be implemented. The SPDC tried to intimidate the Burmese people, but has never tried for a genuine dialogue. We don't enjoy basic rights. The Burmese people are being deprived ofbasic human rights. The National League for Democracy (NLD) is subjected to severe repression. The regime created economic and political chaos, with the result that millions crossed into neighboring countries. Ethnic minorities are being targeted by the regime and they have fled into Thailand by the tens of thousands. I beg neighboring countries to extend humanitarian help to the refugees. The UN resolution on Burma is clear. Help any way you can to enable the UN resolution to be implemented.
  - PBS: Senior of the week, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:06:00] (Box 295, Video-cassette BU091)
    Produced by: PBSUSA
    Father Joseph Lamar of the Mary Knoll Charity in Guatemala, a significant voice in fighting the Unocal Out of Burma Project.
  - Amateur Footage: Footage from a Thai Prison, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:15:00] (Box 295, Video-cassette BU120)
    Produced by: Kevin, Private Footage
  - Earth Rights International: Pipeline Forced Labor, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:30:00] (3 copies) (Box 302, Video-cassette BU121)
    Produced by: Earth Rights International
    Two refugees and the pipeline.
    Denuded forests in Burma.
    Thein Zaw: Since four cuts era. We are between, we were suspected by both side. Killings were rampant. They asked us to construct trails, bunkers and buildings without pay. We have pay for the porter if not we have to go. We have to pay all the construction if not one has to go or is tortured.
    We were responsible for the actions of the Karen National Union (KNU). 200,000 Kat was demanded for an electric post. What I most dislike is unnecessary killing. One officer was killed in an ambush and the army executed four including my two brothers as revenge.
    Pipeline forced labor. Carry military loads for pipeline security. Army maltreated us. Many people are forced to work in pipeline construction. I saw foreigners working in the site. They saw us. I have no idea how to express my feeling. If anyone says there is no forced labor, they are lying. My friend was shot by a soldier and died.
    Zaw: Thai blocked border and refugees were lost in the jungle.
  - National League for Democracy (NLD): Tenth Anniversary of the August 8, 1988 Uprising, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:30:00] (Box 302, Video-cassette BU122)
    Daw Aung San Suu Kyi: "We have fulfilled our promises of the election 1990. But Saw Maung said, I'll transfer power according to the law. Releasing prisoners is not my business. We are in an economic mess. Many social problems. The health care system is in shambles. International investment does not help the people in any way. We must have an accountable government."
    Student demonstration, November, 1996.
    Suu Kyi: "Why is there unrest? Because of discontent. Dialogue is the most humane way to resolve our problems. Speak out for justice. Democracy is a process that needs a lot of hard work."
    Daw Suu's Q and A Over the Fence.
  - ABC: Nightline - Unocal vs. Burmese Peasant, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:22:00] (Box 302, Video-cassette BU123)
    Produced by: Kevin
    A Lawsuit against Unocal's involvement in construction of the Yadana pipeline in Burma. Hosted by Dave Marash. Runtime: 00:22:00.
    Unocal Involvement in Burma, Right or Wrong?
    John Imles: The challenge is, which one to select.
    Unocal was condemned for that.
    Joe Lamar: "Why do you go in there in the first place? Many US companies got out of Burma."
    Imles: "The existence of gas and the market made us decide to do business."
    Burma's peasants charged that Unocal was among the top two companies guilty of forced labor, forced relocation and forced porterage.
    John Doe: "I had to suck my sweat to ease the thirst."
    The account of thousands is uniform. Unocal blamed the military.
    Judge Paez: "Don't buy that. This lawsuit is very significant."
    Tyler Gianinni: "The UN condemned Burma every year."
    US State Department: "The Burmese people continue to live under an extremely oppressive regime."
    Imles: "Economic opportunity must be accompanied by an island of integrity. Unocal is providing health and education."
    The island of integrity was surrounded by a sea of abuse.
    Two witnesses: "We were forced to work and we were not paid."
    He who lies down with dogs gets up with fleas.
    John Doe: "We were treated like slaves." Jane Doe 1: "They took our rice and chickens and burned our homes. They punched me while I was holding my baby. My baby died of a hemorrhage."
    Maureen Aunt Thwin: "Constructive engagement only strengthened State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC) and their money laundering schemes."
    Kelly Quinn speaks next. He is the speaker of ATOM, the union of atomic workers who are opposed to the regime in power in Burma.
    Imles speaks last. He says that the villagers he interviewed said please stay so he stayed.
  - Images Asia: Daw Aung San Suu Kyi message to Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN) leaders, 1997, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:05:00] (2 copies) (Box 296 and 302, Video-cassette BU124)
    Produced by: Images Asia/Altsean
    The regime has mismanaged the resources of the people. State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC) spent much less on education and health. Burma is no credit for ASEAN. Admission to ASEAN makes SLORC more oppressive. The government has to respect the people. Constructive engagement must be constructive for the Burmese people. We want responsible investment.
  - ABC: Nightline - Burma Deception, NTSC VHS [TRT 00:45:00] (Box 302, Video-cassette BU125)
    Produced by: ABC Nightline, 1993
    by Cynthia Jervis
    Product of Burma Issue, (45 Minutes)
    The Pagan plain. A background song, "Let It Be With My Fault."
    The River Moi. An old farmer: "Burmese soldiers burned our house and we ran away."
    A mother: "State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC) bombed from planes." A young Karen Guerrilla.
    A woman: "I was forced to carry ammunitions and rations. Forced porterage has been practiced for a long time. Now it is getting worse. People with incapacities were abandoned. The worst thing is that they use humans as mine sweepers. We ran away whenever we heard the trucks coming. We are starving. "Even children are picked up and killed.
    A Monk: "Civil war was due to ideologies and later caused by army abuses. We never live in peace, always on the run. We do not want to be refugees here."
    There are over 400,000 refugees in Bangladesh and Thailand.
    A Rohinger Leader: "Forced porterage and rapes forced them to flee. My children died while on the run."
    Extreme oppression is applied to the Burmese people. The regime wants total submission to them.
    A border development program was supported by UNDP. A hospital, schools were built.